For me, it was not being invited to a friend's wedding.
有一次，我的一个朋友 没有邀请我参加他的婚礼。
At first, I didn't really mind.
最开始我并不在意。
I thought he was having a small reception.
我想他只是举办了一个小小的聚会。
But then I kept meeting people who were going to the same wedding,
但是后来我遇见了 好多去参加婚礼的人，
and they weren't as close to the groom as I was ...
这些人也并没有 我和新郎的关系那么好，
and I felt left out.
我觉得自己受了冷落，
That really sucked.
非常难受。
It felt really unfair.
感觉很不公平。
For my daughters, Lipsi and Greta, it was last week.
上个礼拜，我的两个女儿， Lipsi和Greta
They were taking turns massaging their mom's back
她们正在轮流用一个按摩棒
with a toy for back rubs,
给妈妈按摩后背。
and then one of the girls felt that the other girl had a longer go.
一个女孩儿感觉另一个 按摩的时间长了一点，
That's when I walk into the room
就在这时我走进了房间，
to find Greta in a rage, shouting, "That's not fair!"
发现Greta开始发火， 大喊着”这不公平！”
and Lipsi in tears,
Lipsi则哭了起来，
and my wife holding a stopwatch
我的妻子只好拿了一块秒表，
to make sure that each girl had precisely one minute on the toy.
确保每个女孩用的时间正好一分钟。
So if you're anything like me or my girls,
如果你是我和我女儿这样的人，
the last thing that upset you
最近一次让你心烦的事，
probably also had to do with unfairness.
很可能也跟不公平有关。
That's because unfairness triggers us so strongly
因为不公平总能让我们反应强烈，
that we can't think straight.
无法理智思考，
We become afraid and suspicious.
我们变得害怕而多疑，
Our unfairness antennae stick up.
对于不公平十分敏感。
We feel pain, and we walk away.
我们感到痛苦，于是避而远之。
Unfairness is one of the defining issues of our society,
不公平是我们社会中的 一个重要问题，
it's one of the root causes of polarization,
它是两极分化的一个根本原因，
and it's bad news for business.
对于企业来讲， 这可不是一个好消息。
At work, unfairness makes people defensive and disengaged.
在工作中，不公平让人们 变得消极而散漫。
A study shows that 70 percent of workers in the US are disengaged,
一项研究表明美国70%的工作者 都存在工作不投入的现象，
and this is costing the companies
而这正在让公司
550 billion dollars a year every year.
每年遭受5500亿美元的损失。
This is, like, half the total spent on education in the US.
这个数字是美国 每年教育经费的一半。
This is the size of the GDP of a country like Austria.
像奥地利这种国家的 GDP也就这么多。
So removing unfairness and promoting fairness
所以消除不公平，推进公平的进程
should be our priority.
应该成为我们的首要任务。
But what does it mean in practice?
但我们又该如何付诸行动呢？
Is it about more rules? Is it about systems?
应该有更多的规定吗？ 是体系的问题吗？
Is it about equality?
是我们的平等出了问题吗？
Well, partly, but fairness is more interesting than rules and equality.
的确，但这只是一部分原因， 公平远比规章制度和平等要复杂。
Fairness works in surprising ways.
公平以一种你意想不到的 方式运作着。
15 years ago, I left a US investment bank
十五年前，我离开了一家 美国的投资银行，
to join a large Italian state-owned oil company.
加入了一个庞大的 意大利国有石油公司。
It was a different world.
工作环境完全不一样。
I thought the key to getting the best performance
我当时想，要有好的表现，
was a risk-reward system
关键就在于一套“风险补偿系统”。
where you could give the high performers bonuses and promotions
在这种体系里，表现好的人 得到报酬和提拔，
and give the underperformers something to worry about.
表现不好的人则得到一些警告。
But in this company, we had fixed salaries
但是在这家公司里， 我们的工资都是固定的，
and lifelong jobs.
有着一份终身工作。
Careers were set,
岗位既然固定了，
so my toolkit wasn't very effective,
我的办法就变得没那么有效了。
and I was frustrated.
我感到很沮丧。
But then I saw that this company was producing some pockets of excellence,
但是后来我发现这家公司 有一些特别的优势，
areas in which they beat the competition
在一些领域里 他们可以打败竞争对手，
in very tough, competitive sectors.
而且是在非常棘手， 竞争激烈的部门。
This was true in trading,
在贸易方面是这样，
in project management --
在项目管理上是这样，
it was very true in exploration.
在勘探方面也是这样。
Our exploration team was finding more oil and gas
我们的勘探团队 发现的石油和天然气
than any other company in the world.
比世界上任何其他公司都要多。
It was a phenomenon.
真是个奇迹。
Everyone was trying to figure out how this was possible.
每个人都想知道这是怎么做到的。
I thought it was luck,
一开始我想这大概是运气吧，
but after each new discovery, that became less and less likely.
但是持续的新发现让这种猜测 变得越来越站不住脚。
So did we have a special tool? No.
那么我们有什么 特别的工具吗？并没有。
Did we have a killer application that no one else had? No.
我们有独一无二的 杀手级应用程序吗？没有。
Was it one genius who was finding oil for the whole team?
是有个天才帮整个团队找到石油吗？
No, we hadn't hired a senior guy in years.
不，我们好几年没有 雇用高级员工了。
So what was our secret sauce?
那么我们的秘诀到底是什么？
I started looking at them really carefully.
我开始非常仔细地研究。
I looked at my friend,
我发现我的朋友，
who drilled seven dry wells,
他打了七口枯井，
writing off more than a billion dollars for the company,
浪费了公司十几亿美金，
and found oil on the eighth.
最后终于在第八口里发现了石油。
I was nervous for him ...
我一直很担心他，
but he was so relaxed.
但他毫不在意。
I mean, these guys knew what they were doing.
这些人完全知道自己在做什么。
And then it hit me: it was about fairness.
接下来我恍然大悟：这就是公平。
These guys were working in a company
这些人是在为一个
where they didn't need to worry about short-term results.
不需要他们考虑 短期结果的公司工作。
They weren't going to be penalized for bad luck or for an honest mistake.
他们不会因为运气不好或者 无意犯的错误而受到惩罚。
They knew they were valued for what they were trying to do,
他们知道，是自己所做的事 让自己受到重视，
not the outcome.
而不是什么结果。
They were valued as human beings. They were part of a community.
他们被当作人来看待。 他们是集体的一部分。
Whatever happened, the company would stand by them.
不论发生什么， 公司都会做他们的后盾。
And for me, this is the definition of fairness.
对于我来说，这就是公平的意义。
It's when you can lower those unfairness antennae, put them at rest.
当你可以放下对不公平的戒备，
Then great things follow.
好事就会随之而来。
These guys could be true to their purpose, which was finding oil and gas.
这些人可以专心工作， 寻找石油和天然气，
They didn't have to worry about company politics or greed or fear.
而不需要担心公司政策， 贪婪或恐惧。
They could be good risk-takers,
他们可以冒更大的险，
because they weren't too defensive
因为他们不用太心存戒备，
and they weren't gambling to take huge rewards.
也不用下很大赌注 来换取高额回报。
And they were excellent team workers.
他们都是非常优秀的团队工作者。
They could trust their colleagues.
他们可以信任自己的同事。
They didn't need to look behind their backs.
他们不需要提防 别人从背后捅刀子。
And they were basically having fun.
而且他们还都很享受工作。
They were having so much fun,
他们非常开心，
one guy even confessed
一个人甚至坦白
that he was having more fun at the company Christmas dinner
相比在家吃圣诞大餐，他更享受
than at his own Christmas dinner.
公司的圣诞晚宴。
(Laughter)
（笑声）
But these guys, essentially, were working in a fair system
但最重要的是，这些人在一个 公平的体系里工作，
where they could do what they felt was right
在这里他们可以 做任何他们认为正确的事情，
instead of what's selfish, what's quick, what's convenient,
而不是那些利己的， 快捷的，方便的事情。
and to be able to do what we feel is right
被允许做我们认为正确的事情，
is a key ingredient for fairness, but it is also a great motivator.
是构成公平的关键因素， 同样也是巨大的动力。
And it wasn't just explorers who were doing the right thing.
不仅仅是这些勘探者们 在做正确的事情。
There was an HR director who proposed that I hire someone internally
曾经有一位人力资源总监 建议我从内部雇佣某个人，
and give him a managerial job.
给他一份管理工作。
This guy was very good, but he didn't finish high school,
这个人很优秀， 但是他高中都没念完，
so formally, he had no qualifications.
所以严格来讲，他并没有资格。
But he was so good, it made sense, and so we gave him the job.
但是他太优秀了，完全能够胜任， 我们就给了他这份工作。
Or the other guy, who asked me for a budget to build a cheese factory
还有一个人曾经向我申请一笔经费， 要建造一座奶酪工厂，
next to our plant in Ecuador, in the village.
就建在厄瓜多尔一个村子里 我们的工厂旁边。
It didn't make any sense: no one ever built a cheese factory.
这简直太不靠谱了， 我们没人修建过奶酪工厂。
But this is what the village wanted, because the milk they had would spoil
但是村民们需要它， 因为他们的牛奶经常坏掉，
before they could sell it, so that's what they needed.
根本卖不完，所以这是他们需要的。
And so we built it.
因此我们建了这座工厂。
So in these examples and many others,
在这类事件中，
I learned that to be fair,
我明白了要想变得公平，
my colleagues and I, we needed to take a risk and stick our head out,
我和我的同事需要 承担风险，跳出规则，
but in a fair system, you can do that.
但在一个公平的体系中， 这样做没问题。
You can dare to be fair.
你可以勇敢地去做。
So I realized that these guys and other colleagues
所以我意识到，这些人 和我的其他同事
were achieving great results, doing great things,
在追求好的结果，做正确的事情，
in a way that no bonus could buy.
这是不能用金钱买到的。
So I was fascinated.
这深深吸引了我。
I wanted to learn how this thing really worked,
我想知道这种事情 到底是如何办到的，
and I wanted to learn it also for myself, to become a better leader.
同时也是为了能让我自己 变成一个更好的领导者。
So I started talking to colleagues, to coaches,
所以我开始和同事，教练，
to headhunters and neuroscientists,
猎头，和神经学家交流。
and what I discovered
我发现，
is that what these guys were up to and the way they worked
这些人做的事和他们工作的方式
is really supported by recent brain science.
是有着最新脑科学理论支持的。
And I've also discovered that this can work at all levels
我还发现这对于各个层级，
in any type of company.
各种公司都适用。
You don't need the fixed salaries or the stable careers.
并不只适用于有着 固定工资和稳定工作的岗位。
This is because science shows
这是因为，科学证明，
that humans have an innate sense of fairness.
人类有与生俱来的公平感。
We know what is right and what is wrong
什么是对的，什么是错的，
before we can talk or think about it.
在谈论或者琢磨它之前， 我们就已经知道。
My favorite experiment
有一个我最喜欢的实验，
has six-month old babies
让六个月大的婴儿，
watching a ball trying to struggle up a hill.
看着一个球努力地 想要爬上一个山坡。
And there's a helpful, friendly square that pushes the ball up the hill,
友好且乐于助人的方块 会帮这个球推上山坡，
and then a mean triangle pushes the ball back down.
而卑鄙的三角则想要 把这个球推下去。
After watching this several times,
数次之后，
they ask the babies to pick,
实验人员让婴儿选择
to choose what to play with.
和谁一起玩，
They can pick a ball, a square or a triangle.
他们可以选择球，方块或者三角。
They never pick up the triangle.
他们从来没有选择过三角。
All the babies want to be the square.
所有婴儿都想和方块一起玩。
And science also shows
科学同样证明，
that when we see or perceive fairness,
当我们看到或察觉到公平的时候，
our brain releases a substance that gives us pleasure,
我们的大脑会释放一种 令我们快乐的物质，
proper joy.
令我们愉悦。
But when we perceive unfairness, we feel pain ...
但是当我们察觉到不公平的时候， 我们会感到痛苦，
even greater pain
甚至要比
than the same type of pain as if I really hurt myself.
有时候真的伤到了自己还要痛苦。
That's because unfairness triggers the primitive, reptile part of our brain,
这是因为不公平刺激了 大脑最原始的那部分，
the part that deals with threats and survival,
那个用于处理威胁和 生存问题的部分。
and when unfairness triggers a threat, that's all we can think about.
当不公平催生了一种 威胁的时候，一切都完了。
Motivation, creativity, teamwork,
动力，创造力，团队合作，
they all go way back.
全都没有了。
And it makes sense that we're wired this way,
我们如此紧张是有道理的，
because we're social animals.
因为我们是群居动物。
We need to be part of a community to survive.
我们需要成为集体的 一部分才能生存。
We're born so helpless
我们生来都是如此弱小，
that someone needs to look after us until we're maybe 10 years old,
可能到十岁 都需要有人照顾我们。
so our brain evolves towards food.
所以我们的大脑向食物进化。
We need to be in that community.
我们需要成为集体的一部分。
So whether I like it or not,
所以不管我喜不喜欢，
not being invited to the friend's wedding,
没有被邀请参加朋友的婚礼，
my lizard brain is generating the same response
我那原始的大脑都会产生反应，
as if I'm about to be pushed out from my community.
让我感觉像被集体排斥了一样。
So science explains quite nicely why fairness is good
因此，科学很好的说明了 为什么公平很好，
and why unfairness makes us really defensive,
为什么不公平让我们如此抵触，
but science also shows that in a fair environment,
但科学同样说明了 在一个公平的环境里，
not only do we all want to be the square,
我们不只是想成为那个方块，
but we tend to be the square,
在潜意识里就是这么认为的。
and this allows other people to be fair in turn.
这让其他人也渐渐地想要变得公平。
This creates a beautiful fairness circle.
这种现象创造了一个积极的公平循环。
But while we start off fair ...
但虽然我们一开始是公平的……
one drop of unfairness contaminates the whole pool,
一颗老鼠屎却能坏了一锅汤，
and unfortunately, there's plenty of drops in that pool.
不幸的是，很多情况下都是如此。
So our effort should be to filter out
所以我们应该致力于
as much unfairness as we can from everywhere,
尽可能地把不公平去掉，
starting from our communities, starting from our companies.
从我们的集体开始，公司开始。
I worry about this a lot because I lead a team of 3,000 excellent people,
我对这些事很担心，是因为我领导着 一个有着三千位优秀员工的团队。
and the difference between 3,000 happy, motivated team workers
最重要的，就是三千名快乐， 充满动力的员工和三千名看着表
and 3,000 clock-watchers is everything.
等着下班的人之间的区别。
So the first thing I try to do in my fairness crusade
所以，在我的公平改革之中， 我尝试的第一件事情就是
is to try to take myself out of the equation.
就是把我自己去掉。
That means being aware of my own biases.
我的意思是了解自己的偏见。
For example, I really like people who say yes
比如，我特别喜欢 那些不管我说什么
to whatever I suggest.
都同意的人。
(Laughter)
（笑声）
But that's not very good for the company
但是这对于一个公司 来说不是什么好事，
and not very good for anyone who has different ideas.
对于那些持有不同意见的人也不好。
So we try to actively promote a culture of diversity of opinions
所以我们想要积极推广 一种包容各种观点
and diversity of character.
和不同性格的文化。
The second thing we do is a little more procedural.
我们做的第二件事情 则有一点程序化。
We look at all the rules, the processes, the systems in the company,
我们检阅所有的规定， 流程，和公司的体制，
the ones we use to take decisions and allocate resources,
那些我们用于做决定 和分配资源的东西，
and we try to get rid of anything that's not very clear,
摒弃掉那些不清楚的，
not very rational, doesn't make sense,
不理性的，不合理的。
and we also try to fix anything that's limiting
我们同样设法修正那些
the transfer of information within the company.
限制公司内部信息传递的东西。
We then look at the culture and the motivation for the same reasons.
我们又以同样的方式 检视公司文化和积极性。
But my point is that however hard you look at the rules,
但我的观点是， 不管你下了多大工夫去修订规则，
the processes, the systems -- and we have to do that --
流程，体系——这些是必要的——
but however hard we look,
但是尽管我们付出很大努力，
we're never going to do enough to get to the real essence of fairness.
我们永远得不到完全的公平。
That's because the last mile of fairness requires something else.
因为达到公平的最后几步 需要一些其他的东西。
It's about what people's emotions are,
这些东西和人们的情绪有关，
what their needs are,
和他们的需求有关，
what's going on in their private lives,
和个人生活有关，
what society needs.
也和社会需求有关。
These are all questions and elements
这些都是很难放进
that are very hard to put into a spreadsheet, into an algorithm.
电子表格，用程序计算的问题。
It's very hard to make them part of our rational decision.
很难把这些变成我们 做理性决策的一部分。
But if we miss these, we're missing key important points,
但是如果我们少了这些， 就会缺失关键点，
and the outcome is likely to feel unfair.
结果就是，人们又有可能感到不公平。
So we should cross-check our decisions with our fairness center switched on.
所以我们需要在有公平意识的情况下， 反复核对我们的决定。
Is it right that this guy should get the job he's really hoping to get?
这个人应当得到那份 他特别想要的工作吗？
Is it right that this guy should be fired?
这个人真的应该被开除吗？
Is it right that we should be charging so much for this product?
我们真的应该在这个产品上 花这么多钱吗？
These are tough questions.
这些都是难题。
But if we take the time to ask ourselves
但是如果我们真的静下来好好问自己
whether the rational answer is the right one ...
合理的答案就是正确的吗……
we all know deep inside what the answer is.
我们其实内心都知道答案是什么。
We've known since we were babies.
我们从婴儿时期就具备了这种能力。
And to know what the right answer is
知道答案是什么，
is pretty cool for decision-making.
对于做决定是很有帮助的。
And if we turn on our hearts,
而且，如果我们敞开心扉，
that's the key to getting the real best out of people,
你就可以看到人们真实，最好的一面，
because they can smell it if you care,
因为如果你真的用心的话， 别人是可以感觉到的。
and only when you really care will they leave their fears behind
只有你真正关心他们的时候， 他们才会放下恐惧
and bring their true selves to work.
并把他们真正的自我用在工作上。
So if fairness is a keystone of life,
所以，如果公平是人生的基石，
why isn't every leader making it their priority?
为什么不是每一个领导都重视它呢？
Wouldn't it be cool to work in a company that was more fair?
在一个更公平的公司工作 难道不是更好吗？
Wouldn't it be great to have colleagues and bosses
如果老板和同事
that were selected and trained for fairness and for character
都是因为公平和人品 被选拔和训练，而不是根据
and not based on 60-year-old GMATs?
60年不变的GMATs，不是很棒吗？
Wouldn't it be nice to be able to knock on the door
可以去敲“首席公平官”的门
of a Chief Fairness Officer?
难道不好吗？
We'll get there, but why is it not happening now?
我们迟早会这样的， 但为什么不能是现在？
Well, partly, it's because of inertia,
有部分原因是人的惰性，
partly, it's because fairness isn't always easy.
部分是因为公平并不总是简单的事。
It requires judgment and risk.
它需要判断，有风险。
Drilling that eighth well was a risk.
打那八口井去寻找石油是有风险的。
Promoting the guy who didn't finish high school was a risk.
提拔高中没毕业的人是有风险的。
Building a cheese factory in Ecuador was a risk.
在厄瓜多尔建一座 奶酪工厂也是有风险的。
But fairness is a risk worth taking,
但是，公平是一个值得尝试的风险，
so we should be asking ourselves,
所以我们需要问自己，
where can we take this risk?
我们在哪些方面可以冒这个险？
Where can we push ourselves a little bit further,
在哪些方面我们可以让自己更进一步，
to go beyond what's rational and do what's right?
突破“合理的事”而去做“正确的事”？
Thank you.
谢谢。
(Applause)
（掌声）